Guide to the Cornwall Artists Collection 1840-2000 MS006 MS006 MS 006
Cornwall Historical Society
Cornwall Artists Collection
1840-2000
Cornwall Historical Society
MS 006
0.5 Linear feet (1 box)
This collection contains documents related to Cornwall artists. Both artists who were Cornwall natives, and those who either moved to or visited the community are present.
Provenance
The collection was formed from loose items formerly stored in miscellaneous boxes, and represent items obtained by historians such as E.C. Starr and Emily E. Marsh, as well as Cornwall Historical Society president Paula S. Holmes.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
"Two known Cornwall natives are included in this collection. Leigh Richmond Miner (1864-1935) was a graduate of the National Academy of Design in New York, and taught art at the Hampton Institute. Miner worked in a number of mediums, but is best known for his photographs of African American and Native American life. Arlington Yutzler (1911-1995), who learned to paint in classes taught in Cornwall by summer resident George Baer, is also represented in this collection.Artists who visited the community include Edward Winsor Kemble (1861-1933), an illustrator who worked on Mark Twain’s The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn and several of Joel Chandler Harris’ Uncle Remus stories. M. Hart Newcomb may have also been a visitor to the community, although little else is known of his background. A print by wildlife painter Jack Murray (1889-1965) is also present, although the terms of its donation to the historical society attribute it to Murray’s wife, Clara Lane Murray.Artists who moved to community include American landscape painter Benjamin Foster (1852-1926), who paintings won widespread acclaim during his lifetime, and New Jersey native Clarence P. Meier (1897-1976), a former cartoonist best remembered in Cornwall for his murals of the community that adorn the walls of the post office. Charlotte Hunnewell Martin (1871-1961) was herself an artist and artisan, but is best remembered as the builder of “The Castle” property and its pottery-works. New York native and current Cornwall resident Tim Prentice, who has worked as both an architect and a sculptor, is also represented in this collection. Items related to James Thurber (1894-1961), best known for his illustrations in The New Yorker are found within this collection, as are materials connected to landscape painter Theodore Van Soelen (1890-1964), who bought property in Cornwall in the 1930s. In 1983, Nora Wise donated two articles on her late husband John Wise (1901-1981) to the historical society. The two owned a home in Cornwall and were instrumental in collecting pre-Columbian art and having it classified as artwork, rather than simply ethnography."
Scope and Content Note
The materials in this collection consists mainly of printed materials by or about these Cornwall artists dating from approximately 1840 to 2000.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged in series by artist then chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 12 series:
Benjamin Foster
E.W. Kemble
Clarence P. Meier
Charlotte Hunnewell Martin
Leigh R. Miner
Clara Lane Murray
M. Hart Newcomb
Tim Prentice
James Grover Thurber
Theodore Van Soelen
John Wise
Arlington Yutzler
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Artists; Cornwall (Conn.); Articles; Correspondence; Cornwall Historical Society; Kemble, E. W. (Edward Windsor), 1861-1933; Foster, Benjamin (1852-1926); Thurber, James, 1894-1961; Prentice, Tim
- Benjamin Foster
  - Article, "An American Landscape Painter," in The Outlook, about Foster, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Image of Foster’s "Evening Mists," in Corcoran Gallery of Art exhibitiom, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mountain (Object item 012)
- E.W. Kemble
  - "The Story of Farmer’s College," in The Cosmopolitan, with illustrations by E.W. Kemble, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clarence P. Meier
  - Newspaper stories about murals painted by Clarence P. Meier, 1951-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4'-6)
  - Letter, and photographs of his work, sent to Clarence P. Meier by Joseph A. Owens, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Color negatives of photographs taken of murals painted by Clarence P. Meier, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Charlotte Hunnewell Martin
  - Information on Charlotte H. Martin’s pottery operation, written by Mr. and Mrs. C.P. Meier, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Leigh R. Miner
  - Notice for Leigh R. Miner’s “Indian Pictures” exhibit, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photography booklet, Everyday Life at Hampton Institute, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Clara Lane Murray
  - Painting, "Scene From Dibble Hill,", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- M. Hart Newcomb
  - Pencil drawing of unknown location, ca. 1840 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Tim Prentice
  - "Kinetic Sculpture" exhibit booklet, Maxwell Davidson Gallery, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- James Grover Thurber
  - Article, "Priceless Gift of Laughter," in Time, featuring a compilation of Thurber illustrations, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Theodore Van Soelen
  - Newspaper stories about murals by Theodore Van Soelen, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
- John Wise
  - Program for commemorative exhibit on John Wise at the Dallas Museum of Fine Arts, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter sent to P.S. Holmes from Nora Wise, about John Wise items donated to Cornwall Historical Society, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Arlington Yutzler
  - Newspaper story about portrait of William Oliver, painted by Arlington Yutzler, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - William Oliver and Grandchild (Object item 004)
- William Ward Beecher
  - In the Likeness of Greenspot, 1980 (Object 1)
    General
    The painting was commissioned for the donor's mother in the likeness of a W.W. Beecher painting she admired titled "Greenspot."
    Gift of R. Furnace, 2016.